<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM 'rfc2629.dtd' []>
<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="std" docName="draft-hzpa-dprive-xfr-over-tls-02" updates="1995">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc private=""?>
<?rfc topblock="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="no"?>
<front>
<title abbrev="XFR-over-TLS">DNS Zone Transfer-over-TLS</title>

<author initials="H." surname="Zhang" fullname="Han Zhang">
<organization>Salesforce</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city>San Francisco, CA</city>
<code></code>
<country>United States</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>hzhang@salesforce.com</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="P." surname="Aras" fullname="Pallavi Aras">
<organization>Salesforce</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city>Herndon, VA</city>
<code></code>
<country>United States</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>paras@salesforce.com</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="W." surname="Toorop" fullname="Willem Toorop">
<organization>NLnet Labs</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<street>Science Park 400</street>
<city>Amsterdam</city>
<code>1098 XH</code>
<country>The Netherlands</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>willem@nlnetlabs.nl</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="S." surname="Dickinson" fullname="Sara Dickinson">
<organization>Sinodun IT</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<street>Magdalen Centre</street>
<street>Oxford Science Park</street>
<city>Oxford</city>
<code>OX4 4GA</code>
<country>United Kingdom</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>sara@sinodun.com</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<author initials="A." surname="Mankin" fullname="Allison Mankin">
<organization>Salesforce</organization>
<address>
<postal>
<street></street>
<city>Herndon, VA</city>
<code></code>
<country>United States</country>
<region></region>
</postal>
<phone></phone>
<email>allison.mankin@gmail.com</email>
<uri></uri>
</address>
</author>
<date year="2019" month="July" day="8"/>

<area>Internet</area>
<workgroup>dprive</workgroup>
<keyword>DNS</keyword>
<keyword>operations</keyword>
<keyword>privacy</keyword>


<abstract>
<t>DNS zone transfers are transmitted in clear text, which gives attackers the
opportunity to collect the content of a zone by eavesdropping on network
connections. The DNS Transaction Signature (TSIG) mechanism is specified to
restrict direct zone transfer to authorized clients only, but it does not add
confidentiality. This document specifies use of DNS-over-TLS to prevent zone
contents collection via passive monitoring of zone transfers.
</t>
</abstract>


</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>DNS has a number of privacy vulnerabilities, as discussed in detail in
<xref target="I-D.bortzmeyer-dprive-rfc7626-bis"/>. Stub client to recursive resolver query
privacy has received the most attention to date. There are now standards track
documents for three encryption capabilities for stub to recursive queries and
more work going on to guide deployment of specifically DNS-over-TLS (DoT)
<xref target="RFC7858"/> and DNS-over-HTTPS (DoH) <xref target="RFC8484"/>.
</t>
<t><xref target="I-D.bortzmeyer-dprive-rfc7626-bis"/> established that stub client DNS query
transactions are not public and needed protection, but on zone transfer
<xref target="RFC1995"/> <xref target="RFC5936"/> it says only:
</t>
<t>&quot;Privacy risks for the holder of a zone (the risk that someone gets the data)
are discussed in [RFC5936] and [RFC5155].&quot;
</t>
<t>In what way is exposing the full contents of a zone a privacy risk? The contents
of the zone could include information such as names of persons used in names of
hosts. Best practice is not to use personal information for domain names, but
many such domain names exist. There may also be regulatory, policy or other
reasons why the zone contents in full must be treated as private.
</t>
<t>Neither of the RFCs mentioned in <xref target="I-D.bortzmeyer-dprive-rfc7626-bis"/>
contemplates the risk that someone gets the data through eavesdropping on
network connections, only via enumeration or unauthorized transfer as described
in the following paragraphs.
</t>
<t><xref target="RFC5155"/> specifies NSEC3 to prevent zone enumeration, which is when queries
for the authenticated denial of existences records of DNSSEC allow a client to
walk through the entire zone. Note that the need for this protection also
motivates NSEC5 <xref target="I-D.vcelak-nsec5"/>; zone walking is now possible with NSEC3
due to crypto-breaking advances, and NSEC5 is a response to this problem.
</t>
<t><xref target="RFC5155"/> does not address data obtained outside zone enumeration (nor does
<xref target="I-D.vcelak-nsec5"/>). Preventing eavesdropping of zone transfers (this draft)
is orthogonal to preventing zone enumeration, though they aim to protect the
same information.
</t>
<t><xref target="RFC5936"/> specifies using TSIG <xref target="RFC2845"/> for authorization of the clients of
a zone transfer and for data integrity, but does not express any need for
confidentiality, and TSIG does not offer encryption. Some operators use SSH
tunneling or IPSec to encrypt the transfer data.
</t>
<t>Because the AXFR zone transfer is typically carried out-over-TCP from
authoritative DNS protocol implementations, encrypting AXFR using DNS-over-TLS
<xref target="RFC7858"/> seems like a simple step forward. This document specifies how to use
DoT to prevent zone collection from zone transfers, including discussion of
approaches for IXFR, which uses UDP or TCP.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;NOT RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this
document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> and
<xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
</t>
<t>Privacy terminology is as described in Section 3 of <xref target="RFC6973"/>.
</t>
<t>Note that in this document we choose to use the terms 'primary' and 'secondary'
for two servers engaged in zone transfers.
</t>
<t>DNS terminology is as described in <xref target="RFC8499"/>.
</t>
<t>DoT: DNS-over-TLS as specified in <xref target="RFC7858"/>
</t>
<t>DoH: DNS-over-HTTPS as specified in <xref target="RFC8484"/>
</t>
<t>XoT: Generic XFR-over-TLS mechanisms as specified in this document
</t>
<t>AXoT: AXFR-over-TLS
</t>
<t>IXoT: IXFR over-TLS
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="use-cases-for-xfrovertls" title="Use Cases for XFR-over-TLS">
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Confidentiality. Clearly using an encrypted transport for zone transfers will
defeat zone content leakage that can occur via passive surveillance.</t>
<t>Authentication. Use of single or mutual TLS authentication (in combination
with ACLs) can complement and potentially be an alternative to TSIG.</t>
<t>Performance. Existing AXFR and IXFR mechanisms have the burden of backwards
compatibility with older implementations based on the original specifications
in <xref target="RFC1034"/> and <xref target="RFC1035"/>. For example, some older AXFR servers don’t
support using a TCP connection for multiple AXFR sessions or XFRs of different
zones because they have not been updated to follow the guidance in [RFC5836].
Any implementation of XFR-over-TLS would obviously be required to implement
optimized and interoperable transfers as described in <xref target="RFC5936"/> e.g. transfer
of multiple zones-over-one connection.</t>
<t>Performance. Current usage of TCP for IXFR is sub-optimal in some cases i.e.
connections are frequently closed after a single IXFR.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="connection-and-data-flows-in-existing-xfr-mechanisms" title="Connection and Data Flows in Existing XFR Mechanisms">
<t>The original specification for zone transfers in <xref target="RFC1034"/> and <xref target="RFC1035"/> was
based on a polling mechanism: a secondary performed a periodic SOA query (based
on the refresh timer) to determine if an AXFR was required.
</t>
<t><xref target="RFC1995"/> and <xref target="RFC1996"/> introduced the concepts of IXFR and NOTIFY
respectively, to provide for prompt propagation of zone updates. This has
largely replaced AXFR where possible, particularly for dynamically updated
zones.
</t>
<t><xref target="RFC5936"/> subsequently redefined the specification of AXFR to improve
performance and interoperability.
</t>
<t>In this document we use the phrase &quot;XFR mechanism&quot; to describe the entire set of
message exchanges between a secondary and a primary that concludes in a
successful AXFR or IXFR request/response. This set may or may not include
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>NOTIFY messages</t>
<t>SOA queries</t>
<t>Fallback from IXFR to AXFR</t>
<t>Fallback from IXFR-over-UDP to IXFR-over-TCP</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>The term is used to encompasses the range of permutations that are possible and
is useful to distinguish the 'XFR mechanism' from a single XFR
request/response exchange.
</t>

<section anchor="axfr-mechanism" title="AXFR Mechanism">
<t>The figure below provides an outline of an AXFR mechanism including NOTIFYs.
</t>
<t><eref target="https://github.com/hanzhang0116/hzpa-dprive-xfr-over-tls/blob/02_updates/02-draft-svg/AXFR_mechanism.svg">Figure 1. AXFR Mechanism</eref>
</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>An AXFR is often (but not always) preceded by a NOTIFY (over UDP) from the
primary to the secondary. A secondary may also initiate an AXFR based on a
refresh timer or scheduled/triggered zone maintenance.</t>
<t>The secondary will normally (but not always) make a SOA query to the primary
to obtain the serial number of the zone held by the primary.</t>
<t>If the primary serial is higher than the secondaries serial (using Serial
Number Arithmetic <xref target="RFC1982"/>), the secondary makes an AXFR request (over TCP)
to the primary after which the AXFR data flows in one or more AXFR responses on
the TCP connection.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t><xref target="RFC5936"/> specifies that AXFR must use TCP as the transport protocol but
details that there is no restriction in the protocol that a single TCP session
must be used only for a single AXFR exchange, or even solely for XFRs. For
example, it outlines that the SOA query can also happen on this connection.
However, this can cause interoperability problems with older implementations
that support only the trivial case of one AXFR per connection.
</t>
<t>Further details of the limitations in existing AXFR implementations are outlined
in <xref target="RFC5936"/>.
</t>
<t>It is noted that unless the NOTIFY is sent over a trusted communication channel
and/or signed by TSIG is can be spoofed causing unnecessary zone transfer
attempts.
</t>
<t>Similarly unless the SOA query is sent over a trusted communication channel
and/or signed by TSIG the response can, in principle, be spoofed causing a
secondary to incorrectly believe its version of the zone is update to date.
Repeated successful attacks on the SOA could result in a secondary serving stale
zone data.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ixfr-mechanism" title="IXFR Mechanism">
<t>The figure below provides an outline of the IXFR mechanism including NOTIFYs.
</t>
<t><eref target="https://github.com/hanzhang0116/hzpa-dprive-xfr-over-tls/blob/02_updates/02-draft-svg/IXFR%20mechanism.svg">Figure 1. IXFR Mechanism</eref>
</t>
<t>
<list style="numbers">
<t>An IXFR is normally (but not always) preceded by a NOTIFY (over UDP) from the
primary to the secondary. A secondary may also initiate an IXFR based on a
refresh timer or scheduled/triggered zone maintenance.</t>
<t>The secondary will normally (but not always) make a SOA query to the primary
to obtain the serial number of the zone held by the primary.</t>
<t>If the primary serial is higher than the secondaries serial (using Serial
Number Arithmetic <xref target="RFC1982"/>), the secondary makes an IXFR request to the
primary after the primary sends an IXFR response.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t><xref target="RFC1995"/> specifies that Incremental Transfer may use UDP if the entire IXFR
response can be contained in a single DNS packet, otherwise, TCP is used. In
fact is says in non-normative language:
</t>
<t>&quot;Thus, a client should first make an IXFR query using UDP.&quot;
</t>
<t>So there may be a forth step above where the client falls back to IXFR-over-TCP.
There may also be a forth step where the secondary must fall back to AXFR
because e.g. the primary does not support IXFR.
</t>
<t>However it is noted that at least two widely used open source authoritative
nameserver implementations (<eref target="https://www.isc.org/bind/">BIND</eref> and
<eref target="https://www.nlnetlabs.nl/projects/nsd/about/">NSD</eref>) do IXFR using TCP by
default in their latest releases. For BIND TCP connections are sometimes used
for SOA queries but in general they are not used persistently and close after
an IXFR is completed.
</t>
<t>It is noted that the specification for IXFR was published well before TCP was
considered a first class transport for DNS. This document therefore updates
<xref target="RFC1995"/> to state that DNS implementations that support IXFR-over-TCP MUST use
<xref target="RFC7766"/> to optimise the use of TCP connections and SHOULD use <xref target="RFC7858"/> to
manage persistent connections.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="data-leakage-of-notify-and-soa-message-exchanges" title="Data Leakage of NOTIFY and SOA Message Exchanges">
<t>This section attempts to presents a rationale for also encrypting the other
messages in the XFR mechanism.
</t>
<t>Since the SOA of the published zone can be trivially discovered by simply
querying the publicly available authoritative servers leakage RR of this is not
discussed in the following sections.
</t>

<section anchor="notify" title="NOTIFY">
<t>Unencrypted NOTIFY messages identify configured secondaries on the primary.
</t>
<t><xref target="RFC1996"/> also states:
</t>
<t>&quot;If ANCOUNT&gt;0, then the answer section represents an
  unsecure hint at the new RRset for this .
</t>
<t>But since the only supported QTYPE for NOTIFY is SOA, this does not pose a
potential leak.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="soa" title="SOA">
<t>For hidden primaries or secondaries the SOA response leaks the degree of lag of
any downstream secondary.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="connection-and-data-flows-in-xot" title="Connection and Data Flows in XoT">

<section anchor="performance-considerations" title="Performance Considerations">
<t>The details in <xref target="RFC7766"/>, <xref target="RFC7858"/> and <xref target="RFC8310"/> about e.g. using
persistent connections and TLS Session Resumption <xref target="RFC5077"/> are fully
applicable to XFR-over-TLS as well.
</t>
<t>It is RECOMMENDED that clients and servers that support XoT also implement
EDNS0 Keepalive [RFC7828].
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="axot-mechanism" title="AXoT mechanism">
<t>The figure below provides an outline of the AXoT mechanism including NOTIFYs.
</t>
<t><eref target="https://github.com/hanzhang0116/hzpa-dprive-xfr-over-tls/blob/02_updates/02-draft-svg/AXoT_mechanism_1.svg">Figure 3: AXoT mechanism</eref>
</t>
<t>All implementations that support XoT MUST fully implement <xref target="RFC5953"/> behavior
on TLS connections.
</t>
<t>Sections 4.1, 4.1.1 and 4.1.2 of <xref target="RFC5936"/> describe guidance for AXFR clients
and servers with regard to re-use of sessions for multiple AXFRs, AXFRs of
different zones and using TCP session for other queries including SOA.
</t>
<t>For clarity we restate here that an AXoT client MAY use an already opened TLS
connection to send a AXFR request. Using an existing open connection is
RECOMMENDED over opening a new connection. (Non-AXoT session traffic can also
use an open connection.)
</t>
<t>For clarity we additionally state here that an AXoT client MAY use an already
opened TLS connection to send a SOA request. Using an existing open connection
is RECOMMENDED over opening a new connection.
</t>
<t>The connection for AXFR-over-TLS SHOULD be established using port 853, as
specified in <xref target="RFC7858"/>, unless there is mutual agreement between the secondary
and primary to use a port other than port 853 for XFR-over-TLS.
</t>
<t>QUESTION: Should there be a requirement that the SOA is always done on a TLS
connection if the XFR is? For the case when no transfer is required this could
be unnecessary overhead.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="ixot-mechanism" title="IXoT mechanism">
<t>The figure below provides an outline of the IXoT mechanism including NOTIFYs.
</t>
<t><eref target="https://github.com/hanzhang0116/hzpa-dprive-xfr-over-tls/blob/02_updates/02-draft-svg/IXoT_mechanism_1.svg">Figure 4: IXoT mechanism</eref>
</t>
<t>The connection for IXFR-over-TLS SHOULD be established using port 853, as
specified in <xref target="RFC7858"/>, unless there is mutual agreement between the secondary
and primary to use a port other than port 853 for XFR-over-TLS.
</t>
<t><xref target="RFC1995"/> says nothing with respect to optimizing IXFRs over TCP or re-using
already open TCP connections to perform IXFRs or other queries. We provide
guidance here that aligns with the guidance in <xref target="RFC5936"/> for AXFR and with
that for performant TCP/TLS usage in <xref target="RFC7766"/> and <xref target="RFC7858"/>.
</t>
<t>An IXoT client MAY use an already opened TLS connection to send a IXFR request.
Using an existing open connection is RECOMMENDED over opening a new connection.
(Non-IXoT session traffic can also use an open connection.)
</t>
<t>An IXoT client MAY use an already open TLS connection to send an SOA query.
Using an existing open connection is RECOMMENDED over opening a new connection.
</t>
<t>An IXoT server MUST be able to handle multiple IXoT requests on a single TLS
connection, as well as to handle other query/response transactions over it.
</t>
<t>An IXoT client MAY keep an existing TLS session open in the expectation it is
likely to need to perform an IXFR in the near future. The client may use the
frequency of recent IXFRs to calculate an average update rate and then use
EDNS0 Keepalive to request an appropriate timeout from the server (if the
server supports EDNS0 Keepalive). If the server does not support EDNS0
Keepalive the client MAY keep the connection open for a few seconds (<xref target="RFC7766"/>
recommends that servers use timeouts of at least a few seconds).
</t>
<t>An IXoT client MAY pipeline IXFR requests for different zones on a single TLS
connection. AN IXoT server MAY respond to those requests out of order.
</t>

<section anchor="fallback-to-axfr" title="Fallback to AXFR">
<t>Fallback to AXFR can happen, for example, if the server is not able to provide
an IXFR for the requested SOA. Implementations differ in how long they store
zone deltas and how many may be stored at any one time.
</t>
<t>After a failed IXFR a IXoT client SHOULD request the AXFR on the already open
TLS connection.
</t>
</section>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="zone-transfer-with-dot--authentication" title="Zone Transfer with DoT - Authentication">

<section anchor="tsig" title="TSIG">
<t>TSIG <xref target="RFC2845"/> provides a mechanism for two parties to exchange secret keys
which can then be used to create a message digest to protect individual DNS
messages. This allows each party to authenticate that a request or response (and
the data in it) came from the other party, even if it was transmitted-over-an
unsecured channel or via a proxy. It provides party-to-party data
authentication, but not hop-to-hop channel authentication or confidentiality.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="tls" title="TLS">

<section anchor="opportunistic" title="Opportunistic">
<t>Opportunistic TLS <xref target="RFC8310"/> provides a defence against passive
surveillance, providing on-the-wire confidentiality.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="strict" title="Strict">
<t>Strict TLS <xref target="RFC8310"/> requires that a client is configured with an
authentication domain name (and/or SPKI pinset) that should be used to
authenticate the TLS handshake with the server. This additionally provides a
defense for the client against active surveillance, providing client-to-server
authentication and end-to-end channel confidentiality.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="mutual" title="Mutual">
<t>This is an extension to Strict TLS <xref target="RFC8310"/> which requires that a client is
configured with an authentication domain name (and/or SPKI pinset) and a client
certificate. The client offers the certificate for authentication by the server
and the client can authentic the server the same way as in Strict TLS. This
provides a defense for both parties against active surveillance, providing
bi-directional authentication and end-to-end channel confidentiality.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="ip-based-acl-on-the-primary" title="IP Based ACL on the Primary">
<t>Most DNS server implementations offer an option to configure an IP based Access
Control List (ACL), which is often used in combination with TSIG based ACLs to
restrict access to zone transfers on primary servers.
</t>
<t>This is also possible with XoT but it must be noted that as with TCP the
implementation of such and ACL cannot be enforced on the primary until a XFR
request is received on an established connection.
</t>
<t>If control were to be any more fine-grained than this then a separate port would
be required for XoT such that implementations would be able to refuse
connections on that port to all clients except those configured as secondaries.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="zonemd" title="ZONEMD">
<t>Message Digest for DNS Zones (ZONEMD) <xref target="I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-zone-digest"/> digest
is a mechanism that can be used to verify the content of a standalone zone. It
is designed to be independent of the transmission channel or mechanism, allowing
a general consumer of a zone to do origin authentication of the entire zone
contents. It is not considered suitable for highly dynamic zones. It is
complementary the above mechanisms and can be used in conjunction with
XFR-over-TLS but is not considered further.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="comparison-of-authentication-methods" title="Comparison of Authentication Methods">
<t>The Table below compares the properties of each of the above methods in terms of
what protection they provide to the secondary and primary servers during XoT in
terms of:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>'Data Auth': Authentication that the DNS message data is signed by the party
with whom credentials were shared (the signing party may or may not be party
operating the far end of a TCP/TLS connection in a 'proxy' scenario). For the
primary the TSIG on the XFR request confirms that the requesting party is
authorized to request zone data, for the secondary it authenticates the zone
data that is received.</t>
<t>'Channel Conf': Confidentiality of the communication channel between the
client and server (i.e. the two end points of a TCP/TLS connection).</t>
<t>Channel Auth: Authentication of the identity of party to whom a TCP/TLS
connection is made (this might not be a direct connection between the primary
and secondary in a proxy scenario).</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>It is noted that zone transfer scenarios can vary from a simple single
primary/secondary relationship where both servers are under the control of a
single operator to a complex hierarchical structure which includes proxies and
multiple operators. Each deployment scenario will require specific analysis to
determine which authentication methods are best suited to the deployment model
in question.
</t>
<t><eref target="https://github.com/hanzhang0116/hzpa-dprive-xfr-over-tls/blob/02_updates/02-draft-svg/Properties_of_Authentication_methods_for_XoT.svg">Table 1: Properties of Authentication methods for XoT</eref>
</t>
<t>Based on this analysis it can be seen that:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>A combination of Opportunistic TLS and TSIG provides both data authentication
and channel confidentiality for both parties. However this does not stop a
MitM attack on the channel which could be used to gather zone data.</t>
<t>Using just mutual TLS can be considered a standalone solution if the
secondary has reason to place equivalent trust in channel authentication as
data authentication e.g. the same operator runs both the primary and
secondary.</t>
<t>Using TSIG, Strict TLS and an ACL on the primary provides all 3 properties for
both parties with probably the lowest operational overhead.</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="policies-for-both-axfr-and-ixfr" title="Policies for Both AXFR and IXFR">
<t>We call the entire group of servers involved in XFR (all the primaries and all
the secondaries) the 'transfer group'.
</t>
<t>Within any transfer group both AXFRs and IXFRs for a zone SHOULD all use the same policy e.g. if AXFRs use AXoT all IXFRs SHOULD use IXoT.
</t>
<t>In order to assure the confidentiality of the zone information, the entire
transfer group MUST have a consistent policy of requiring confidentiality. If
any do not, this is a weak link for attackers to exploit.
</t>
<t>A XoT policy should specify
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>If TSIG is required</t>
<t>What kind of TLS is required (Opportunistic, Strict or mTLS)</t>
<t>If IP based ACLs should also be used.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>Since this may require configuration of a number of servers who may be under
the control of different operators the desired consistency could be hard to
enforce and audit in practice.
</t>
<t>Certain aspects of the Policies can be relatively easily tested independently
e.g. by requesting zone transfers without TSIG, from unauthorized IP addresses
or over cleartext DNS. Other aspects such as if a secondary will accept data
without a TSIG digest or if secondaries are using Strict as opposed to
Opportunistic TLS are more challenging.
</t>
<t>NOTE: The authors request feedback on this challenge and welcome suggestions of
how to practically manage this.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="multiprimary-configurations" title="Multi-primary Configurations">
<t>Also known as multi-master configurations this model can provide flexibility
and redundancy particularly for IXFR. A secondary will receive one or more
NOTIFY messages and can send an SOA to all of the configured primaries. It can
then choose to send an IXFR request to the primary with the highest SOA (or
other criteria e.g. RTT).
</t>
<t>When using persistent connections the secondary may have a TLS connection
already open to one or more primaries. Should a secondary preferentially
request an IXFR from a primary to which it already has an open TLS connection
or the one with the highest SOA (assuming it doesn't have a connection open to
it already)?
</t>
<t>Two extremes can be envisaged here. In the first case the secondary continues to
use one persistent connection to a single primary until it has reason not to.
Reasons not to might include the primary repeatedly closing the connection, long
RTTs on transfers or the SOA of the primary being an unacceptable lag behind the
SOA of an alternative primary.
</t>
<t>At the other extreme a primary could keep multiple persistent connections open
to all available primaries and only request IXFRs from the primary with the
highest serial number. Since normally the number of secondaries and primaries in
direct contact in a transfer group is reasonably low this might be feasible if
latency is the most significant concern.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="implementation-considerations" title="Implementation Considerations">
<t>TBD
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="implementation-status" title="Implementation Status">
<t>The 1.9.2 version of
<eref target="https://github.com/NLnetLabs/unbound/blob/release-1.9.2/doc/Changelog">Unbound</eref>
 includes an option to perform AXFR-over-TLS (instead of TCP). This requires
the client (secondary) to authenticate the server (primary) using a configured
authentication domain name.
</t>
<t>It is noted that use of a TLS proxy in front of the primary server is a simple
deployment solution that can enable server side XoT.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">
<t>TBD
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">
<t>This document specifies a security measure against a DNS risk: the risk that an
attacker collects entire DNS zones through eavesdropping on clear text DNS zone
transfers. It presents a new Security Consideration for DNS. Some questions to
discuss are:
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Should DoT in this new case be required to use only TLS 1.3 and
higher to avoid residual exposure?</t>
<t>How should padding be used in IXFR?</t>
<t>Should there be an option to 'pad' an AXFR response (i.e. a set of AXFR
responses on a given connection) to hide the zone size?</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
<t>The authors thank Benno Overeinder, Shumon Huque and Tim Wicinski for review and
discussions.
</t>
</section>

<section anchor="changelog" title="Changelog">
<t>draft-hzpa-dprive-xfr-over-tls-01
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Substantial re-work of the document.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>draft-hzpa-dprive-xfr-over-tls-01
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Editorial changes, updates to references.</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>draft-hzpa-dprive-xfr-over-tls-00
</t>
<t>
<list style="symbols">
<t>Initial commit</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

</middle>
<back>
<references title="Normative References">
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.bortzmeyer-dprive-rfc7626-bis.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.vcelak-nsec5.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1995.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2845.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5077.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5155.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5936.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6973.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7858.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8310.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8484.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8499.xml"?>
</references>
<references title="Informative References">
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dnsop-dns-zone-digest.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1982.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1996.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5953.xml"?>
<?rfc include="https://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7766.xml"?>
</references>

</back>
</rfc>
